Silvia De Sojo Caso

sdsc@dtu.dk | LinkedIn | Twitter | Mastodon | GitHub

Affiliations: DTU Social Complexity Lab, Copenhagen Center for Social Data Science, MIT Senseable City Lab Keywords: Human Mobility, Network Science, Complex Systems, Urban Space, Human Behavior, Inequalities

SCIENTIFIC FOCUS AREAS

My research focuses on understanding behavioural inequalities across genders and diverse groups. I analyze large-scale data sets, including GPS traces from over 1M individuals, smartphone app usage, and online user-generated data. Employing a cross-disciplinary approach, I integrate methodologies such as network analysis, bayesian inference, and matching techniques. In my Ph.D. I explore the gender gaps in human mobility across countries, cities, and socio-economic groups. Using causal inference methods, I examine the influence of household responsibilities, division of labour, and safety perceptions on gender differences in mobility.

EDUCATION

Ph.D. student - Social Complexity Lab, DTU Compute

April 2022 - Present

Thesis: The gender gaps in human mobility

Copenhagen, Denmark

Advisors: Laura Alessandretti and Sune Lehmann

Visiting Ph.D. student - Senseable City Lab, MIT

August 2024 - Present

Collaborators: Paolo Santi, Timur Abbiasov, Arianna Salazar-Miranda, Carlo Ratti Cambridge, MS, United States

MSc in Business Analytics - DTU, Danmarks Tekniske Universitet

March 2022

Thesis in collaboration with: Social Complexity Lab

Copenhagen, Denmark

Thesis Grade: 12/12

BSc in Industrial Technology Engineering - UPC, Universitat Politècnica de Catalunya

June 2016

Thesis in collaboration with: Analysis of Complex Data for Business Decisions Lab and HP Inc

Barcelona, Spain

Thesis Grade: 10/10 with Honors

Professional Experience

Business Operations and Finance Analyst - UNDP, United Nations

January 2020 - June 2020

Project force for the development of State Revenue Authority offices in South Sudan

Copenhagen, Denmark

Project and Program Manager - HP Sales Ops, HP Inc

July 2017 – July 2019

Define the strategy, lead projects, and coordinate project teams (20+ employees in 4 countries)

Barcelona, Spain

Business Planner and Analytics - HP Sales Ops, HP Inc

July 2016 - June 2017

Graduate Program. Driving planning, forecasting, and analytics activities within e-commerce

Barcelona, Spain

Lean Six Sigma Project Manager - HP Customer Support, HP Inc

September 2015 – June 2016

Leading a Lean Six Sigma Project within HP Supply Chain

Barcelona, Spain

SUPERVISION AND TEACHING

Teaching - Teacher Assistant, DTU

September 2020 - Present

 $Computational\ Social\ Science\ (BSc),\ Social\ Graphs\ and\ Interactions\ (MSc),$

Data Science for Mobility (MSc) and Introduction to Business Analytics (MSc)

Supervision - Co-supervising 4 MSc Theses and 1 Special Course, DTU

Ambition and success in physical activity goal setting - María Jiménez Álvarez, Unveiling the lexical and content gender biases in Wikipedia Pages - Alejandra Navarro Castillo, Understanding the gender gaps in Wikipedia collaboration networks - Joana Soler Torramilans, The motherhood penalty in mobility - Mia Jørgensen

SELECTED TALKS

Conferences: Selected as one of 16 among 900 submissions for the "young researchers lightning talk" plenary session at the International Conference in Computational Social Science - IC2S2 Copenhagen (Jul 2023), Contributed Talk at IC2S2 Copenhagen (Jul 2023), Contributed Talk at Conference on Complex Systems - CCS Palma (Oct 2022)

Invited Speaker: Network Science Institute - Northeastern University, Boston (September 2024), Complexity Science Hub - Vienna (Nov 2023), Dublin Cycling Campaign - Inclusive and Accessible Mobility (Oct 2023), NERDS - IT University of Copenhagen (Jul 2022), Analysis of Complex Data for Business Decisions - UPC (May 2016)

Summer Schools and Workshops: ICTP Workshop on Inequality Across Scales, Space, Time and Domains (April 2023), Oxford Summer School in Economic Networks (June 2023), IceLab Camp (Sep 2022), Lipari Summer School (Jul 2022)

Grants, Scholarships & Awards

International Conference in Computational Social Science - Honorable Mention

July 2023

Honrable mention received after presenting during the Young Researchers Lightning Talk at IC2S2 2023

DTU Compute Ph.D. Bazaar - Best Pitch Award

June 2022

Awarded the jury's best pitch award during DTU Compute Ph.D. Bazaar, competing against ≈ 25 participants

STIBO FONDEN IT Scholarship - Travel Grant

May 2024

The scholarship covered 50,000 DKK during the PhD external stay at MIT Senseable City Lab

Det Unge Akademi - Danish Research Environment of the Year 2023

July 2023

The Social Complexity Lab won the the award and won DKK 10,000 for an academic social event

Danish Data Science Academy - Travel Grant

September 2022

 $The\ grant\ covered\ 15,000dkk\ for\ travel,\ accommodation,\ and\ conference\ fee\ for\ my\ attendance\ at\ CCS$

Danish Data Science Academy - Event Grant

May 2023

The grant covered 35,000dkk for organizing three DataBeers Copenhaguen events

DTU Compute PhD School - Event Grant

Nov 2022

The grant covered 8,000dkk for organizing one DataBeers Copenhaguen event

Oxford Summer School in Economic Networks - Attendance Bursary

February 2023

Selected for a 50% bursary on the tuition fee for my attendance at the summer school

PhD Scholarship funded by the Inge Lehmann project

April 2022

The scholarship covers a 3-year Ph.D. stipend for project "Gender Gaps in Human Mobility"

HP Sales Operations - Leading the Way Award

June 2019

Selected among all employees within the department (≈ 400) for a monetary reward and leadership recognition

Universitat de Barcelona - Special Mention in Research for Peace Award

June 2011

Award for high school students' research projects to strengthen the culture of peace through research

COMMUNITY & LEADERSHIP

Reviewer for journals

February 2024 - Present

Royal Society Open Science, Nature - Scientific Reports, NPJ Complexity

Lead Organiser of DataBeers CPH - Copenhagen

Aug 2022 - Present

Non-profit community organizing events and talks in the scope of Big Data and Data Science

Elected Member of the Ph.D. Committee - DTU Compute

Jan 2023 - Dec 2023

Acting as the voice of DTU Ph.D. students and influencing the Ph.D. education

IC2S2 Volunteer - DTU Compute

May 2023 - July 2023

Organizing the flagship conference on Computational Social Science (\approx 700 attendees)

Moderator for social research community - mastodon @datasci.social

Jan 2023 - Present

The mastodon server is dedicated to researchers and practitioners in human-centric data science

Professional Representative - Agency for Quality in the University System

Jan 2018 - May 2018

Member of the committee approving the accreditation of official bachelor's and master's degrees

HP Code Wars Volunteer - HP Inc

March 2015, 2016

Organising the computer programming competition hosting high school students (\approx 300 attendees)

${\rm Skills}$

Programming Languages: Python, R, Julia

Frameworks: Apache Spark, NumPy, Pandas, Matplotlib, SciPy, scikit-learn, NetworkX, Keras

Official Accreditations: PRINCE2 Foundation (sponsor: United Nations), Lean Six Sigma Green Belt (sponsor: HP)

 $Languages: \ Catalan\ (Native) \cdot Spanish\ (Native) \cdot English\ (Fluent) \cdot French\ (B1) \cdot Danish\ (A2)$